[SPEAKER_01]: Recently, you have been speaking a lot about the relationship between citta and mano, the wild animal and the trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where and how does the body, kāyā, come in here?
[SPEAKER_01]: And how would you describe the fetter of sakāyādhiti in the context of citta and mano?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where does the body come in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it comes in by being there, by being your outline, being your backdrop,
[SPEAKER_00]: Being the place where you find the symptoms of your untamed mind, agitations, arousals, anxieties, all of that's manifested in the body, all of that's bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you think that by observing body and bodily sensations, you're going to get to the root of those symptoms, that's basically sending you completely on the wrong track.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I say, like, hindrances are bodily, in a sense that hindrances are inseparable from the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they will... they will be manifesting in the body, those pressures.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you think you're gonna find them in the body through your observation, as I said, you're already... you're already missing... missing the... missing the... missing the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is a difference between
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a difference between body being lived and discerned passively, on the level of the background of your experience, and there is a difference between you actively trying to observe your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever the Buddha is talking about contemplation of the body, it's actually always done in that passive indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because each time you try to directly observe it, it becomes an object of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes a basically tactile sensation, visual... basically become object of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not the body as the saḷāyatana.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the... these fields of six senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five senses and the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what people don't understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, of course, you have the body passively and then you want to look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you think you're looking at the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is,
[SPEAKER_00]: You, you're looking, driven by your attention, intention, sorry, intention, and attention actually, attention and intention to to see the body on the, as an object of your senses, makes it something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes it something that's actually not your body there and then, while you're looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the body,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or all the other five senses are always the negative, are always that which cannot be observed directly through the senses or the other senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first and foremost, is the person has to learn to stop trying to see the body, observe the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's why the whole confusion of watching sensations and contemporary techniques, they think they're observing the body the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just observing the sense objects that they mistakenly took to be that which their body is there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bodies that
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is always there, which you can always see with the corner of your eye, which you could always perceive these things in, that are caused by changes of mood, hindrances and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you try to grasp it directly, attend to it directly, it won't be the body you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although you might well delude yourself in believing it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what was the other question?
[SPEAKER_01]: How you would describe the fetter of saccadity in the context of citta and manu?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, let's put it this way, in relation to what I just answered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, imagine your entire life you are going around driven by the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just in terms of your passions and desires, that's obviously the fuel, but in terms of your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, most people would think the body is that which I observe, not that which I kind of peripherally quote-unquote feel or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's what I can measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what I can see in you, in him, in me, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, through going around, seeking and becoming dependent on the level of the sense objects, that's where your consciousness gets established.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that's what becomes a threshold for existence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I say, for like a really, really untrained mind, for that person, even their own thoughts are felt like, oh, they're not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's real, it's only what's palpable, what can be measured, seen, smelled, tasted, touched and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody goes around like that, unrestrained in those ways, the threshold of their existence is determined by these, as I said, measurable things, well, that, pretty much, in and of itself, is where the sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_00]: They put it out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They assume it to be out there in that physical, material world that I'm witnessing, that I'm perceiving, that I'm engaging with.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether I do so or not, that matter outside of me exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: And assuming the existence of anything external to your five aggregates is the core of attavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they might not... people might not necessarily think, oh, I exist independent of this, or I don't exist independent of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, if your mind is dependent on sense objects past a certain threshold, you would have perverted the picture sufficiently enough that external... the assumption of external is where your actual being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, nobody goes around thinking, oh, I'm an annihilationist or I'm an eternalist.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you look at the views, where the emphasis is, they will fall in one of these two categories.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no third option.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the third option is to be neither, but you can't just figure that out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just figure out the middle ground and then build from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to actually and actively withdraw yourself from the dependence on the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what gives you the possibility of learning the balance of the middle ground, which is the middle way, which is then you could truly say, oh, I neither assume everything is outside of me, nor do I assume everything is in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if a person tries to figure that out before they would have actually tamed their senses to some extent, it's just going to be another standpoint that's going to fall back onto either too external or a bit too internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to figure it out, start sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the virtue and contain the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the mind settles in, as the taming starts taking place, then you get to recognize your assumption of the external existence as gratuitous as it always was.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could still have those thoughts, but they won't carry the same weight as they do for somebody who has been acting in an unrestrained manner for so long.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that weight is placed through the emphasis of your desires and passions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's kind of indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: That desire immediately induces the wrong view or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it keeps you in that perverted state of what comes first, what comes second, what's actually more fundamental, what isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, your views will just naturally start to grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Atthavāda is basically assuming a standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't even say assuming yourself, because again, people think like, well, I don't think about myself being... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just assuming a standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: In any direction, that is assumed to be external to your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, your experience as a whole is placed second to the standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that cannot be the case, because it doesn't matter how objective your standpoint is, it's still your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking the outside of this experience as a whole is yet another image, another experience of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't outrun it, or outthink it, or step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always fully confined within that.